Guide to the Marvin Gettleman Papers TAM.523
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Marvin Gettleman Papers
1976-2000
TAM.523
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
1.0 linear feet in one manuscript box and one media box.
Marvin Gettleman (1933-) is an emeritus professor of history at the Polytechnic Institute of New York University. The collection reflects Gettleman's work with the New York Faculty Committee for Non-Intervention in Central America and the Caribbean and also contains audio materials collected by Gettleman on a range of topics related to the left. The New York Faculty Committee for Non-Intervention in Central America and the Caribbean fought for human rights in Central America in the 1980s, with a focus on conditions in El Salvador and Guatemala. The group organized visits to the region and advocated for changes in United States foreign policy. The files contain reports, notes, newspaper and magazine clippings, correspondence, petitions, and research materials. Audio materials in the collection contain recordings of interviews, debates, and lectures. Four interviews document the experiences of those effected by the Rapp-Coudert Committee of the early 1940s. Recordings of debates and lectures document the study of movements on the left in North America, Latin America, and Europe from 1976-2000.
Gettleman, Marvin E.
New York Faculty Committee for Non-Intervention in Central America and the Caribbean.
Access Restrictions
Content is open for research without restrictions.
Due to the fragile nature of the original audio media, master cassettes must be digitized before access by researchers. To request digitization of materials, please contact tamiment.wagner@library.nyu.edu.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series:
Series 1. New York Faculty Committee for Non-Intervention in Central America and the Caribbean
Series 2. Audio Materials.
Files within each series are arranged chronologically.
Biographical/Historical note
Marvin Gettleman (1933-) is an emeritus professor of history at the Polytechnic Institute of New York University. He has been involved with many causes on the left, including the New York Faculty Committee for Non-Intervention in Central America and the Caribbean in the 1980s.
Scope and Contents note
The collection contains notes, clippings, articles, correspondence, and petitions documenting the activities of New York Faculty Committee for Non-Intervention in Central America and the Caribbean and human rights in Latin America.
Audio materials in the collection contain recordings of interviews, debates, and lectures documenting the study of movements on the Left in North America, Latin America, and Europe from 1976-2000. Four interviews document the experiences of those effected by the Rapp-Coudert Committee of the early 1940s.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Marvin Gettleman, November, 2009.
Faculty for Human Rights in El Salvador and Central America.; El Salvador |x Politics and government |y 1979-1992.; Guatemala |x Politics and government |y 20th century.; Human rights |z El Salvador.; Human rights |z Guatemala.; New York (State). Legislature. Joint Legislative Committee to Investigate the Educational System of the State of New York; United States |x Foreign relations |z El Salvador.; United States |x Foreign relations |z Guatemala.
- New York Faculty Committee for Non-Intervention in Central America and the Caribbean, 1977-1985
  Historical/Biographical Note
  The New York Faculty Committee for Non-Intervention in Central America and the Caribbean was an organization focused on human rights and United States foreign policy in Central America in the 1980s. Their activities included the investigation of human rights abuses, lobbying the United States government, and organizing visits to El Salvador and Guatemala. The organization worked in cooperation with Faculty for Human Rights in El Salvador and Central America (FACHRES).
  Scope and Contents note
  The series contains reports, notes, newspaper clippings, correspondence, articles, and petitions documenting the activities of New York Faculty Committee for Non-Intervention in Central America and the Caribbean and human rights in Latin America. The documents focus primarily on conditions in Guatemala and El Salvador. Notes and correspondence document members' visits to El Salvador and Guatemala. The series also contains research materials for writings on Central America, such as a photocopy of a special issue of Guatemalan Church in Exile titled "Guatemala, a New Way of Life: The Development Poles." Members corresponded with elected officials about United States foreign policy, and these materials are present. There are also documents from Faculty for Human Rights in El Salvador and Central America (FACHRES), the Peace Lobby, and other organizations.
  - 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Undated (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
- Audio Materials, 1976-2000
  Scope and Content Note
  This series contains recordings of interviews, debates, and lectures. Four interviews document the experiences of those effected by the Rapp-Coudert Committee of the early 1940s. Recordings of debates and lectures document the study of movements on the left in North America, Latin America, and Europe from 1976-2000.
  - E.P. Thompson at New York Socialist Conference, Feb 1976 (Box 2)
  - Karen Spaulding on history of Peru and Professor Woods, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Interview with Edward Rosen (Rapp-Coudert), 1977 (Box 2)
  - Dorothy Healy and Michael Harrington at ITT Forum, Jan 16, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Interview with Oscar Shaftel (Rapp-Coudert), 1978 (Box 2)
  - Interview with Sidney Shanker (Rapp-Coudert), 1978 (Box 2)
  - Music recorded in visit to Lutheran Refugio outside of San Salvador, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Mark Naison, "Thinking About American Communism," Brecht Forum, Sep 29, 1988 (Box 2)
  - World Historical Conference, Montreal Canada, 1995 (Box 2)
  - New York Marxist School, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Havard Debates on the origins of the New Left, Apr 17, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Sam Bowles on political economy at John Jay College, undated (Box 2)
  - Marvin Gettleman, debates and lectures in Massachusetts, undated (Box 2)
  - New York Marxist School [Brecht 3/10], undated (Box 2)
  - Science and Society event featuring Eric Foner and Eleanor Leacock, undated (Box 2)
  - Interview with Dudley Strauss (Rapp-Coudert), undated (Box 2)